A Guide to the Broad Street Improvements-Papers of Sue Bachtel, 1963-1991
Mary Riley Styles Public Library
Mary Riley Styles Public Library
Broad Street Improvements-Papers of Sue Bachtel, 1963-1991
Falls Church History Room, Mary Riley Styles Public Library
Record Group 1-1
17 folders in 2 boxes
Papers of Sue Bachtel
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research use.
Scope and Content
These two boxes contain Sue Bachtel’s chronological files of her involvement with the process of designing, planning, funding, and determining the scope of Broad Street Improvements during the 1980s. Bachtel was a Council Member during much of the effort to widen and improve West Broad Street from West Street to almost Haycock Road. These files do not constitute a definitive reporting of the process of Broad St improvements, nor do they contain all the reports that are referred to in the documents as attachments.
These files do not constitute a definitive reporting of the process of Broad St improvements, nor do they contain all the reports that are referred to in the documents as attachments.
Contents List
- Broad St. Improvements -- 1963-1980, 7 items (Box-folder 1-1)
  - June 16, 1980 letter from Harry Wells to Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments
  - February 21, 1979 Memo from Virginia Department of Highways and Transportation (VDH&T) on review of feasibility studies
  - March 27, 1978 Resolution 78-9 authorizing engineering study of Broad St in City of Falls Church
  - June 14, 1976 Ordinance No. 732 for council-approved citizen boards and commissions
  - July 11, 1973 letter from VDH&T re Rt 66/Rt 7 interchange
  - July 3, 1973 letter from Louis Blair (mayor) to Va Highway Commissioner
  - 1963 Falls Church Traffic and Parking Survey prepared by VDH&T
- Broad St. Improvements –1981, 32 items (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Resolution requesting VDH&T to establish an engineering study of Broad St., February 9
  - Memorandum from City Manager to Chairmen of commissions and board on BSIP, February 10
  - Letter from VDH&T to City Manager, February 19
  - Timeline BSIP – Local Phase, February 25
  - Letter from VDH&T to Mayor, March 5, 1981
  - Letter from Ronal Sendak to Sue Bachtel, March 6, 1981
  - Agenda for meeting of Advisory Committee, March 12
  - Minutes of Broad St. improvement meeting, March 25, 8 pages
  - Notice of public meeting, March 26
  - List of Materials for March 26 public meeting, draft, 9 pages
  - List of Materials for March 26 public meeting, final, 14 pages
  - BSIP Information Survey, March 26
  - Notes of presentation to the pre-allocation hearing of April 8
  - Memorandum and notice of BSIP Advisory Committee meeting, April 2
  - Presentation to Commissioner, etc. for the April 8 hearing, draft
  - Presentation to Commissioner, etc. for the April 8 hearing, final
  - Memorandum, Map and Data Collection Phase to staff from Ron Sendak, April 9
  - Summary of minutes of April 30 meeting
  - Summary and Analysis of Citizen Problem Identification from survey, April 30, 5 page
  - Guidelines for Master Landscape Planning, Shirley Street memorandum, April 30
  - Letter to Sue Bachtel with attached Summary and Analysis of Citizen Problem Identification from survey, May 27
  - Agenda for BSIP Advisory Committee meeting, May 27
  - Sue Bachtel’s meeting notes from May 27 committee meeting, 10 pages
  - Minutes of meeting, May 27
  - Summary minutes, BSIP special meeting June 11, 7 pages
  - 2nd copy of summary minutes, June 11 with request for corrections
  - City Manager letter to Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments, June 16, 7 pages
  - Excerpt from minutes, September 1, 1938
  - Agenda BSIP Advisory Committee meeting, June 29
  - Agenda BSIP Advisory Committee meeting, July 7
  - Current cost estimate chart, July 7
  - Minutes, BSIP Advisory Committee, July 7
  - Memorandum Broad St. project school concerns, July 10
- Broad St. Improvements –1981, 15 items (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Minutes, BSIP Advisory Committee, draft, July 13
  - Agenda, special meeting, July 14
  - Memorandum from Shirley Street, City Arborist, Existing Trees on Broad St., July 14
  - Memorandum, Involvement with Fairfax County on Haycock Rd, July 16
  - VDH&T letter to Ron Sendak, July 17, 1981
  - Agenda, BSIP Citizen’s Meeting, July 23
  - Village Preservation and Improvement Society (VPIS) notice of public hearing, July 17
  - Notice of 7/23/1981 public hearing by Council
  - List of Materials for public meeting, July 23
  - Proposed Talking Paper for public meeting, July 23
  - Staff Proposals to be presented to the public meeting, July 23, 52 pages
  - Information package, public meeting, July 23, 11 pages
  - Broad Street Improvement Project Options for Consideration with drawings, 2 copies, July 23
  - Notes of Sue Bachtel from public meeting, July 23
  - Statements and comments at the 7/23 public meeting, July 31, 11 pages
- Broad St. Improvements -- 1981, 26 items (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Memorandum about informational package, July 27
  - Agenda for July 28 meeting
  - Memorandum about contractor work statement, August 1981
  - Memorandum from Ron Sendak to the City Manager on funding, August 5
  - Memorandum on VDH&T conversation from John Cameron, August 6
  - Letter revising proposal from Land Design/Research Inc. (LDR) to Ron Sendak, August 6
  - Bachtel notes, August 7
  - Letter from Falls Church City School Board voicing concerns, August 11
  - Memorandum to Broad Street Improvement Program (BSIP) Advisory Committee, August 12
  - Memorandum to BSIP Staff for 9/3 presentations, August 26, 2 items
  - Letter from Planning Engineer VDH&T with accident analysis, September 3
  - Letter/Proposal for Phase III Streetscape Plans from LDR, September 3, 1981
  - Minutes of 9/3/81 BSIP Advisory Committee
  - Traffic Counter Worksheet, 4/20-4/26/1981
  - Memorandum to Ron Sendak from RJ Durgin on revised cost estimate, September 7
  - Cost estimates, 8/13/1988(?), 8/81, 9/81 3 items
  - BSIP Advisory Committee Minutes of Meeting, September 8
  - Draft CFC Goals and Objectives, 9-10-1981
  - Draft letter with recommendations to Mayor from BSIP Advisory Committee, September 17
  - Notice of meeting from Ron Sendak to BSIP, September 18
  - Summary Report of BSIP Advisory Committee with Recommendations to City Council, September 28, 40 pages
  - Alternative Position paper by Sue Bachtel, September 28, 9 pages
  - Notes from Dan Arms to BSIP committee, September 28
  - Project time elements, VDH&T, September 18
- Broad St. Improvements -- 1981, 19 items (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Memorandum from John Wood to Mayor and City Council without packet of attachments
  - Letter to Mayor and Council from Louis Olom regarding BSIP, September 28, 5 pages
  - CBC Newsletter with Discussion Paper by Conrad Fritsch on BSIP, October 1981
  - The Village Way (VPIS newsletter), message from President on BSIP, October 1981
  - Notice to Citizens, Businessmen and Landowners regarding BSIP, October 13
  - The Village Way, follow-up on public hearings on BSIP, November 1981
  - Handwritten by Sue Bachtel notes from work session, November 6, 7 pages
  - Letter to Planning Commission from Sue Bachtel regarding Broad St. safety issue, November 10
  - Letter from Sue Bachtel to Ed Strait with information on Broad St., November 12
  - Washington Post and Arlington Journal clippings, November 1981, 3 pages
  - Copy of Falls Church Advertiser "Viewpoint" submission by Sue Bachtel, November 30
  - Resolution approving proposals of BSIP, draft, December 9, 12 pages
  - Letter from Sue Bachtel to Mayor and Council, draft December 14
  - Proceedings of December 14 Council meeting, 10 pages
  - List of residents who spoke in opposition to the 5-Lane/"Compromise" Plan at Council meeting, December 14
  - Drawings of Broad St. "Typical Sections," 16 pages
  - Approved Plan for Route 7 (Broad Street) Improvement Program, City of Falls Church, December 14, 28 pages
- Broad St. Improvements –1982, 30 items (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Broad St. Issue—Election ’82—Sequence of Events list. January 5 Resolution of amending the transportation element of the master plan as it relates to Broad Street, January 11
  - Recommended changes to the Route 7 (Broad Street) Improvement Program, no date
  - Public hearing on amendments to the Master plan relating to the transportation elements, January 11
  - Alert: The Broad Street Issue!, January 1982
  - Letter to VDH&T from city manager, January 27
  - Letter to mayor from Bachtel, February 5
  - Memorandum and Board of Trade clipping to city manager from office of business development, February 19
  - Letter to John Newell from Henry Bibber, March 22
  - Memorandum about 1982 preallocation hearing, March 22
  - Letter to VDH&T from mayor, April 13
  - Letter from Rockville, Maryland planner to FCC planning director, April 13
  - Letter from FCC planning director to Rockville planner, April 16
  - Copy of Northern Virginia Sun (NVS) clipping “Broad Steet Plan Opposed", May 15
  - Copy of Falls Church News Advertiser (FCNA) clipping “VPIS set to launch 2nd attach on Broad St. plan," May 20-27
  - Editorial, FCNA, May 20-27
  - Copy FCNA article, June 10-17
  - Copy NVS editorial, June 30
  - Letter to council from VDH&T with tentative allocations for transportation, July 15, 9 pages
  - Letter to VDH&T from director of public works, July 22
  - Response to director of public works from VDH&T, August 6
  - Letter from Mayor to VDH&T, August 6, 6 pages
  - Letter from minority floor leader to mayor, August 11
  - Letter to mayor from VDH&T commissioner, August 13
  - FCNA clipping “State rejects large portion of Broad Street project," August 26
  - VPIS minutes, September 1982
  - Journal clipping “Road construction projects threatened," November 8
  - Letter from city manager to highway commissioner, November 18
  - Copy of Washington Post (WP) “Metro’s effect limited on Falls Church," December 1
  - Sue Bachtel’s notes from council meeting with VDH&T, December 3, 6 pages
- Broad St. Improvements – 1983 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - List of chronological documents re Broad St. issue, prepared May 1983, 6 pages
  - Contents page, but not followed by any contents (?)
  - Letter from Bachtel to Vincent Callahan, January 7
  - Memorandum to planning commission from planning director on Resolution on Broad St. improvements, January 13
  - Arlington Journal clipping on Fairfax Drive, January 17
  - Memorandum on status of BSIP from city manager to mayor and council, March 10, 5 pages
  - Statement by Louis T. Olom to Virginia State Highway Commission, March 30, 9 pages
  - Bachtel letter to VDH&T, March 30
  - Four constituent letters to State Highway Commission, March 28, 29, 30
  - Quote from National Trust for Historic Preservation, April 6
  - Four clippings, April 6, 13
  - Bachtel notes to Hal Silverstein, April 10
  - Bachtel correspondence with journalists, April 10, 3 pages
  - Letter from VDH&T to city manager, April 15
  - Letter from VPIS to mayor and council, April 25
  - Clippings on super trucks, April 8, 3 pages
  - VDH&T map of highways and trucks allowed, no date
  - Memorandum larger trucks on non-interstate roadways, April 14
  - Resolution opposing the use of rout 7 by tandem trailer trucks, April 21
  - DOT’s 1983 Appropriation Act and copy of Public Law 97-424, January 6, 4 pages
  - Copy of Federal Register, February 3 and April 5, truck size and weight policy, 3 pages, 9 pages
  - Letter from highway commissioner to Louis Olom, May 1
  - WP clipping on big rigs, May 4
  - Statement of Olom to VDH&T, May ?
  - Duplicate of Journal clipping
  - Letter from minority floor leader, Vincent Callahan, to Bachtel, April 18
  - Bachtel memo to file re phone call with planner VDH&T, early May
  - VPIS resolution, May 12
  - Broad Street – traffic count comparison summary, May 22
  - Broad Street – traffic count comparison, data sheet, May 22
  - Bachtel letter to Callahan, May 23
  - Bachtel letter to VSH commissioner, May 24
  - Letter and six-year VDH&T plan from Callahan to Bachtel, June 7
  - Memorandum to city manager from planning director: proposal to establish study for West Falls Church metro station area, June 9
  - Quote and Letter to mayor and council from VPIS, 5 pages
  - Proceedings of city council meeting, June 13
  - Notes from Elizabeth Graham testimony before council, June 13
  - Traffic count data, revised June 1, 2 pages
  - Notice of VPIS presentation to council
  - Summary notes on Broad Street petition discussion, June 14, 3 pages
- Broad St. Improvements – 1983 continued (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Memorandum from vice mayor to mayor and council, Resolution on Broad Street Improvement, June 17, 9 pages, includes copy of the following item
  - Memorandum from planning director to city manager, explanation for draft Resolution, June 17, 5 pages
  - Bachtel’s annotated copy of June 17 Resolution, 5 pages
  - Mimeographed copy of adopted Resolution, June 27, 4 pages
  - Letter to Bachtel from DuVal on Senate campaign contribution, June 30
  - Final report: Northern Virginia Metrorail Mode of Access Study, July 29, 49 pages
  - VPIS mailing: Question and Answers on Broad Street, no date
  - Clipping, WP article on narrowing Arlington Ridge Rd., July 10
  - Memorandum from planning director to director of public works, reducing traffic on W Annandale Rd, July 14
  - VPIS Broad Street proposal review, July 16, 13 pages
  - Clipping, Fairfax Journal, metro parking lots, August 1
  - Clipping, WP widening Rt. 50, August 8
  - Annotated agenda from Citizens Advisory Committee on Transportation (CACT), August 10
  - Letter to VPIS members on Broad St. widening, August 13, 8 pages
  - Letter from Bachtel about VDH&T expenditure schedule, August 16
  - Memorandum to CACT from Wallace Nickel, October, 4 pages
  - Copy of FC News Advisor clipping, Bad Intersection, October 6
  - Assumption work sheet, October 30
  - Bachtel notes of presentation to League of Women Voters, November 9,6 pages
  - WP clipping, November 10
  - Traffic analysis by Wallace Nickel sent to Bachtel, November 14
  - Bachtel notes from CACT public hearing, November 16
  - Bachtel Broad St. review memorandum to CACT, November 16, 6 pages
  - Bachtel letter to treasurer, November 17
  - Letter to the editor by Louis T. Olom, November 18
  - Memorandum from planning director to city manager about speeding vehicles, November 18
  - Fairfax Journal clippings on local development (Rosslyn, Braddock Road) projects, December 1, 2
  - CACT recommendation, December 7
  - Memorandum from planner to director of planning department, CACT meeting, December 9, 17 pages
  - League of Women Voters position paper, no date
  - Memorandum from CACT to planning commission on Resolution 83-29, December 14, 4 pages
- Broad St. Improvements – 1984, Petition (Box-folder 1-9)
  - City of Falls Church street maps
  - Pages of 800+ signatures opposing widening of Broad St
- Broad St. Improvements – 1984 (Box-folder 2-10)
  - Journal clipping, January 30
  - Memorandum from chief dispatcher to chief of police, 1981-1983 traffic violation table, early 1984
  - Fairfax Journal clipping, February 6
  - Copies of handwritten Bachtel letters, February 4, 13 pages
  - Proceedings of city council meeting, February 13
  - Bachtel letter to DuVal, February 19 and copy of same
  - Unsent letter to John, February 19, 5 pages
  - Unsent letter to Carol, February 19, 3 pages
  - Unsent Bachtel letter to Gary Knight, February 19
  - Letter to Bachtel from Charles Hedetniemi, February 20
  - Minutes of Business and Professional Development Commission, February 21, 3 pages
  - List of businesses opposed to the widening of Broad St.
  - City of Falls Church map with notes
  - Letter from Delegate Vincent Callahan to Bachtel, February 27
  - Memorandum from chairman, Business and Professional Development Commission to mayor and council, March 8
  - Bachtel letter to chairman, Arlington County Board, April 13, 2022 WP clipping, April 13, 2022
  - Fairfax Journal clipping, early 1984
  - Proposed conceptual landscape master plan presented to VPIS, April 4, 27 pages
  - Fairfax Journal clippings, May 9, July 2
  - VDH&T guidelines for widths and traffic barriers with cover letter, July 18, 8 pages
  - VDH&T 1984-1985 allocations, July 19
  - WP clipping, August 6
  - Memorandum from city manager to mayor and council, August 8 and copy
  - Bachtel letter to mayor and council, September 19
  - 3 traffic pattern drawings
  - Letter from Gary Knight to Bachtel, October 7
  - Proposed changes to West Broad St traffic circulation, November 14, 9 pages
  - Letter from mayor to Bachtel, September 28
  - Memorandum from city manager to various organizations on proposed changes, September 28, 12 pages
  - Two drafts of letter to city manager from VPIS, October
  - Letter to Bachtel from city manager, October 1
  - Four pages of October 22 City Council meeting minutes
  - Memorandum from VDH&T without attached 76th biennial report, October 29
  - Letter from Winter Hill Condominium to city manager with attachments, November 11, 18 pages
  - Memorandum from CACT to city manager, November 19
  - Proposed changes to West Broad St. Traffic Circulation, November 14, 9 pages
  - Memorandum from business and Professional Development Commission to mayor and council, November 21
  - Bachtel’s comments on staff comments, November 17
  - Notes on VDH&T preliminary plans, November 18
  - Memo to planning commission from Bachtel, November 19
  - VPIS letter to planning commission, November 21, 6 pages
  - Unapproved draft of planning commission meeting, December 17, 6 pages
- Broad St. Improvements – 1985 (Box-folder 2-11)
  - Proceedings of city council meeting, January 14, 1985, 14 pages
  - Handwritten notes, January 22
  - Memorandum on Street Tree Project, January 25
  - Council minutes, page 14, January 28
  - Letter to state urban engineer from mayor, January 30, 3 pages
  - Fairfax Journal clipping, February 5
  - Letter from Winter Hill Community Associations to mayor and council, February 7
  - Notice of planning commission appointments, February 11
  - Draft letter from VPIS to city council, April 15
  - Letter from Ed Strait to Bachtel, May 22, 8 pages
  - Memorandum on Streetscape Plan Project, May 28
  - VPIS comments on June 5 briefing session
  - Bachtel notes, June 5
  - Letter to Bachtel, June 6
  - Notes dated June 1985
  - Bachtel script to council meeting, June 10
  - Memorandum to Business and Professional Development Commission from Bachtel, June 11
  - Memorandum to city council from Bachtel, June 12
  - VPIS flyer mailed to citizens June 28
  - Letter to business owners from economic development coordinator, June 12
  - Notice from Business and Professional Development Commission to owners, June 13
  - Sample map, June
  - Bachtel letter to economic development coordinator, June 17
  - Notes, June
  - Press release, Broad St. meetings schedule, June 19, 2 copies
  - Attitudinal survey, June
  - List of petition group, June 19
  - Draft survey from economic development coordinator, June 20
  - Handwritten comments citizen, June 24
  - Revised Broad St. Schedule, June 24
  - VPIS notice to citizens, late June
  - Draft business survey, June 26, 3 pages
  - List of attendees, June 28
  - List of attendees, June 30
  - Memorandum on Streetscape Program Study Design, July 3
  - WP clipping and copy, July 4
  - WP clipping with notes and research, July 4
  - Copy of Northern Virginia Sun clipping, July 6
  - Bachtel letter, July 7
  - Copy of Journal clipping, July 8
  - Mayor letter to Bachtel with Streetscape attachment, July 10
  - Traffic Projections, July 1985
  - Fairfax Journal clipping, July 11
  - Copy of Evening Star clipping, March 25, 1964
  - Planning Commission Statement of Charles King, Jr., July 15, 5 pages
  - Bachtel letter to economic development coordinator, July 16
  - 3 WP clippings, July 18, 20
  - Northern Virginia Sun clipping, July 20
  - Traffic Projections, July 1985, 8 pages
  - Bachtel letter to economic development coordinator, July
  - Handwritten notes, July 22, 23
  - City estimates, July 23
  - 3 clippings, July 22, 23
  - Bachtel comments on city manager statement at council meeting, July 23
  - Clipping, 2 copies, July 24
  - Note, July 31
  - Design Review and Staff Recommendations, July 1985
- Broad St. Improvements – 1985 continued (Box-folder 2-12)
  - VPIS flyer to citizens, August
  - VPIS letter and survey to property owners, August 1
  - Handwritten letter to mayor from Marie Kent, August 6
  - Bachtel comments, August 3
  - Planning Commission Recommendations, August 7
  - Sun clipping, August 7
  - Citizen letters to council, August 9, 10, 12
  - Notes, August 12
  - Bachtel letter to council, August 12
  - Proceedings of council meeting, August 12
  - VPIS president letter to members, August 13, 7 pages
  - Fairfax Sun clipping, August 14
  - WP clipping August 15
  - Fairfax Journal clipping and copy, August 21
  - Bachtel note to VPIS, August 28
  - Memorandum from city manager to superintendent of schools, August 29
  - Letter to Bachtel, August 31
  - Letter to mayor from schools, September 5
  - Bachtel statement to council, September 9
  - Ed Strait letter to council, September 9
  - Memorandum from city manager to council, September 9
  - Proceedings of city council meeting, September 9
  - Bachtel notes on council decision, September 9
  - Northern Virginia Sun clipping, September 9
  - Fairfax Journal clipping, September 11
  - WP clipping, September 12
  - City policy statement concerning vehicular access to West Falls Church metro, September 12
  - Fairfax Sun letter to the editor, September 17
  - Letter to Bachtel, September 18
  - Arlington Journal letter to the editor, September 23
  - Letter and attachments from director of public works to VDH&T, September 23
  - Letter from VDH&T to Mary Nickel, October 1
  - Notes on transportation commission, October, 2 pages
- Broad St. Improvements – 1986 (Box-folder 2-13)
  - Letter to Virginia Department of Transportation and Public Safety, March 26
  - Memorandum to Pethtel from VDH&T, May 29
  - Letter to Olom from office of the Governor, June 18
  - Letter to Olom form Farradyne Systems, August 11
  - Bachtel letter to Streetscape committee, September 16
  - Memorandum to council from city manager, September 18
  - Streetscape Plan for West Broad Street, December 1986
  - Draft of Falls Church Planning Commission meeting, December 15
- Broad St. Improvements – 1987 (Box-folder 2-14)
  - Statement of FC Chamber of Commerce on streetscape plan, January 23
  - WP clipping, February 5
  - Bachtel notes, February nd, February 23, February 25
  - Ray Stewart, VPIS, statement March 2
  - Memorandum from streetscape committee to city council, March 5
  - Preliminary statement of architectural advisory board on draft streetscape proposal, March 9, 2 cc
  - Notes to Ed from Bachtel, March 17
  - VPIS memo to mayor and council, Marchh 18
  - Copy of VPIS statement to Bachtel, March 20
  - Second draft, April 7
  - Mayor’s statement for pre-allocation hearing, April 7
  - Bachtel letter to Commission, April 9
  - Memorandum from city manager to mayor, April10
  - Letter from mayor to VDH&T April 14
  - Architectural Advisory Board Statement, April 20
  - Broad Street streetscape and roadway plans, April 24
  - Memorandum from streetscape committee to mayor and council, April 27
  - Bachtel letter to VDH&T, May 7
  - Letter to Bachtel from VDH&T, May 21
  - Streetscape critique summaries, June 9
  - WP clipping, July 2
  - N.Va. Sun Clipping, july 22
  - VPIS letter to city council, July27
  - N.Va. Sun, clipping, August 12
  - WP clippings, August 13
  - Fairfax Journal letter to the editor, August 20
  - Mayor’s letter to office of the governor, October 5
  - N.Va. Sun clippings, November 7, November 21